Guide to the Leopold Haimson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Menshevik Project,1890s-1977(Inter-University Project on the History of Menshevik Movement)
  - Subseries III.3: Archive on the History of Menshevism, 1898-1972
    - Sub-subseries III.3.4: "Biographical Dictionary,"1940s-1962
      Comprises of materials for one of the Project's major activities - creation of the Mensheviks biographical dictionary. Contains typescripts of Menshevik biographies; personal cards with key biographical, bibliographical, and reference data; and individual files with Mensheviks' bio-bibliographical and reference data including autobiographies, questionnaires, articles, obituaries, and other publications, mostly from Sotsialisticheskii vestnik (holograph manuscripts and notes, typescripts, clippings, printed material). Files arranged according to Russian alphabet. Materials on Georgian Mensheviks are part of Sub-subseries III.3.7: Georgian collection (boxes 55-57). More information on Mensheviks' biographies can be found in memoirs, interviews, and in the general files of the Menshevik Project.
      - Plans for structure and composition of the Dictionary (Box 51, Folder 1)
      - Introduction by G. Aronson (Box 51, Folder 1)
      - Notes (Box 51, Folder 1)
      - List of planned biographies (Box 51, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence
        (See also: Sub-subseries III.3.7: Georgian collection--Biographical materials--Materials for the "Biographical Dictionary of Mensheviks." Box 57, Folders 19-20)
        - Circular letters issued by G. Aronson and L. Kristoff, 1961-1962 (Box 51, Folder 3)
        - Questionnary (Box 51, Folder 3)
      - Personal cards
        - A-B (Box 51, Folder 4)
        - V-G (Box 51, Folder 5)
        - D-E (Box 51, Folder 6)
        - Zh-I (Box 51, Folder 7)
        - K-L (Box 51, Folder 8)
        - M-O (Box 51, Folder 9)
        - P-R (Box 51, Folder 10)
        - S-T (Box 51, Folder 11)
        - U-Ts (Box 51, Folder 12)
        - Ch-Ia (Box 51, Folder 13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 51, Folder 14)
        - Pseudonyms (Box 51, Folder 14)
        - Georgian Mensheviks: see Sub-subseries III.3.7: Georgian collection--Biographical materials--"Materials for the Biographical Dictionary of Mensheviks"( Box 57, Folders 19-20)
      - Individual Files (Box 51)
        - Ab-An (Box 51, Folder 15)
        - Ar-At (Box 51, Folder 16)
        - B (Box 51, Folder 17)
        - V (Box 52, Folder 1)
        - Garvi (Box 52, Folder 2)
        - Ge-Gu (Box 52, Folder 3)
        - Dalin (Box 52, Folder 4)
        - Dan (Box 52, Folder 5)
        - Denike (Box 52, Folder 6)
        - Do-Du (Box 52, Folder 7)
        - Dvinov-Dz (Box 52, Folder 8)
        - Z-I (Box 52, Folder 9)
        - K (Box 52, Folder 10)
        - L (Box 52, Folder 11)
        - M (Box 52, Folder 12)
        - Nikolaevsky-No (Box 52, Folder 13)
        - P (Box 52, Folder 14)
        - R (Box 52, Folder 15)
        - S-Khe (Box 52, Folder 16)
        - Khinoi (Box 52, Folder 17)
        - Ts-Ch (Box 52, Folder 18)
        - Sh-Shch (Box 52, Folder 19)
        - Various: article on Bund and those who where killed in Vorkuta (Box 52, Folder 20)
      - Biographies of Mensheviks, (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 52, Folder 21-26)
        (Biographical compilations; 3 versions. Arranged in Russian alphabetical order)
      - Biographies of Mensheviks (cont.) (Box 53, Folder 1-2)
      - Comments to the Dictionary by G. Aronson and B. Nikolaevsky's,March 15, 1962, (typescript) (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Sub-subseries III.3.5: Bibliography on the History of Menshevism prepared by Anna Burgina with assistance of B.Nikolaevsky, 1960s
      Includes typescript with holograph notes of the Bibliografiia po istorii men’shevizma, Haimson’s preface, and book reviews.
      - Manuscript "Bibliografiia po istorii men'shevizma", (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 53, Folder 4)
        (In Russian)
      - Preface by L.Haimson (Box 53, Folder 5)
      - Book reviews, (reprints, photocopies) (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Sub-subseries III.3.6: Seminars, 1960-1968
      Transcripts of seminar discussions of various of the Project studies and comments on Mensheviks talks and writings (typescripts; some with holograph corrections). Arranged in chronological order. Audio records of seminars (reel-to-reel audio tapes) were removed and stored along with other audio materials (see Series XIV: Audio materials).
      - 1960
        - Lande seminar, June 10: Discussion of the Menshevik reaction after October 1917 (Box 53, Folder 7)
        - Sapir seminar, July 7: Discussion after Sapir's report (Box 53, Folder 8)
        - Aronson seminar, October 28: Outline for discussion of Aronson's paper "K istorii pravogo techeniia sredi men'shevikov" by L.Haimson (Box 53, Folder 9)
          ("The history of the right wing of Menshevism")
        - Schwarz seminar, November 18: Schwartz's report on the chapter 5 of "Sovet rabochikh deputatov", discussion, and comments (Box 53, Folder 10)
          ("The Soviet of workers' deputies")
        - Dalin seminar, November 25: Discussion of Dalin's paper (Box 53, Folder 11)
        - Aronson seminar, December 15: Critique of Aronson's "The Mensheviks in 1905" (Box 53, Folder 12)
      - 1961
        - Dvinov seminar, January 27: Discussion of Dvinov's "Pervaia voina i rossiiskaia sotsial-demokratiia" (Box 53, Folder 13)
        - Dalin seminar, April 8: Critique of Dalin's manuscript of "Men'shevizm v period sovetskoi vlasti" (Box 53, Folder 14)
          ("The Mensheviks in the Soviet period")
      - 1961 (cont.) (Box 54)
        - Dvinov seminar, April 15: Report and discussion on "Pervaia mirovaia voina i Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokratiia", glava 4 "V bor'be za Internatsional" (Box 54, Folder 1)
          ("World War I and the Russian Social-Democrats," chapter four "The Strugle for International")
        - Schwarz seminar, April 21: Presentation and discussion on "Gaponovskaia organizatsiia 1905 g." (Box 54, Folder 2)
          ("The Gapon Movement in 1905")
      - 1962
        - Dvinov seminar, January 19: Discussion of the last chapter of his "Voina i rossiskaia sotsial-demokratiia" (Box 54, Folder 3)
          ("World War I and the Russian Social-Democrats")
        - Schwarz seminars:
          - February 9
            - Discussion of his paper on "Sotsial-demokratiia i zubatovskoe dvizhenie" (Box 54, Folder 4)
              ("Social-Democracy and the Zubatov movement")
            - Critique of S. Schwartz's manuscript on the Gapon movement (Box 54, Folder 5)
          - December 18: Discussion of "Osnovnaia kontseptsiia revoliutsii", (typescript; also included L.Haimson's letter with comments) (Box 54, Folder 6-7)
            (Audiorecord of this seminar: see Series XIV: Audiomaterials--Subseries XIV.3: Seminars, Box 161)
      - 1964
        - Lande seminar, January, 25: Discussion of his work, (typescript) (Box 54, Folder 8)
        - Denike seminar, April 11: Discussion of his work, (typescript) (Box 54, Folder 9)
          (Audiorecord of this: see Series XIV: Audiomaterials--Subseries XIV.3: Seminars, Box 161)
        - Volin seminar, May 2: Discussion of chapters 6 and 7 of his work, (typescript) (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - 1968 May 20. Audiorecord of untitled seminar: see Series XIV: Audiomaterials--Subseries XIV.3: Seminars, Box 162
    - Sub-subseries III.3.7: Georgian Collection, 1894-1965
      Consists of materials on Georgian Menshevism and the Party’s members. Files include correspondence; holograph manuscripts and typescripts of writings and documents, mostly collected and translated by V.Tsuladze and G. Eradze (except Zhordania's materials); bibliography; and biographical data. Arranged by type of material.
      - Correspondence, 1961-1970
        - Arsenidze, Razhden, 1961-1965
          - Aronson, Grigorii, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 1)
          - Haimson, Leopold, 1961-1962 (Box 55, Folder 1)
          - Kamermakher, Iuliia, 1963, 1965 (Box 55, Folder 1)
        - Eradze, Georgii, 1961-1963
          - Aronson, Grigorii, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 2)
          - Haimson, Leopold, 1961-1963 (Box 55, Folder 2)
          - Kamermakher, Iuliia, 1963 (Box 55, Folder 2)
        - Tsintsadze, Noe, 1961-1963
          - Aronson, Grigorii, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 3)
          - Haimson, Leopold, 1961-1963 (Box 55, Folder 3)
        - Tsuladze, Vasilii, 1962-1965
          - Haimson, Leopold, 1962-1963 (Box 55, Folder 4)
          - Kamermakher, Iuliia, 1963-1965 (Box 55, Folder 5)
        - Uratadze, Dato and Madee. Correspondence with L.Haimson, 1962-1970 (Box 55, Folder 6)
        - Zhordania, Inna. Correspondence with L. Haimson, and I.Kamermakher, 1961-1964 (Box 55, Folder 7)
      - Writings and documents:
        - Ebanoidze, L. "Organizatsiia bol'shevikov v Gruzii v period 1905-1907gg.",1959 (Box 55, Folder 8)
          (excerpts from the book)
        - Georgadze, Gr.
          - "Obrazovanie kruzhkov i organizatsii" (Box 55, Folder 9)
          - "Obshchestvennye vzaiootnosheniia v Gruzii 1864-1905gg." (Box 55, Folder 10)
            (excerpts from the book made by V.Tsuladze)
        - Khundadze, S. Notes about N. Zordania: see Zhordania, Noe--Supplement (Box 57, Folder 13)
        - "Kratkaia istoriia Gruzinskoi Sotsial-Demokraticheskoi Partii." Paris, 1933 (Box 55, Folder 11)
        - Listovka Kavkazskogo Soiuza RSDRP k organizovannym rabochim g. Tiflisa o prichinakh rospuska Tifliskogo Komiteta RSDRP I obrazovaniia novogo, February 1905, (holograph manuscript) (Box 55, Folder 12)
        - Makharadze, Filipp. "Organizatsiia RSDRP" (Box 55, Folder 13)
          (excerpts from his book 1905 god v Zakavkazie, 1926
        - Mgeladze, Las. Unpublished memoirs (Box 55, Folder 14)
          (excerpts; translated into Russian by G. Eradze)
        - "Obshchii obzor o s'ezdakh i konferentsiiakh Sotsialdemokraticheskoi Partii Gruzii do revoliutsii 1917 goda" (Box 55, Folder 15)
        - Proklamatsiia Batumskogo Komiteta Kavkazskogo Soiuza RSDRP k batumskim rabochim o partiinykh raznoglasiiakh, April 1905 (Box 55, Folder 16)
        - "Svedeniia o konferentsii zakavkazskikh sotsial-demokraticheskikh organizatsii" (Box 55, Folder 17)
          (from Golos Sotsialdemokrata, No 25, May 1911 Paris)
        - Tsereteli, Iraklii. "Vospominaniia detstva", (holograph notes) (Box 55, Folder 18)
          (written by his sister E.G. Tsereteli)
        - Tsuladze, Vasilii
          - Autobiography (Box 55, Folder 19)
          - "Bol'shevizm v Gruzii" (Box 56, Folder 1)
          - "Deiatel'nost' gruzinskoi S.-D. partii ot marta 1917 g. do maia 1918 g." (Box 56, Folder 2)
          - "Nachalo osnovaniia partii" (Box 56, Folder 3)
          - "Natsional'nyi vopros" (Box 56, Folder 4)
        - Uratadze, Grigorii. "Moi vospominaniia"
          - Manuscript, (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 56, Folder 5-7)
          - Preface by L.Haimson, (typescript; photocopy of galley proofs with holograph corrections) (Box 56, Folder 8)
          - Haimson's notes (Box 56, Folder 9)
        - Žhordania, Noe
          - "Moia zhizn'" ("Moe proshloe"). Memoirs, 1939
            (translated from Georgian by Inna Zhordania and P. Kvitaishvili)
            - Manuscript, (typescript with holograph corrections and carbon copy) (Box 56, Folder 10-13)
            - Comments and additions (Box 56, Folder 14)
            - Preface by L.Haimson, (typescript with holograph corrections; photocopy of galley with holograph corrections) (Box 57, Folder 1)
            - Book reviews (Box 57, Folder 2)
            - Audiorecord: Memoirs of Noah Zhordania read by Ina Zhordania: see Series XIV: Audiomaterial--Subseries XIV.1: Memoirs reading (Box161)
          - Articles, (holograph manuscripts, typescripts)
            (collected, translated, and handwritten by V. Tsuladze)
            - "Duma i politika," 1908 (Box 57, Folder 3)
            - "Ekonomicheskoe preuspeianie i natsional'nost'," 1894 (Box 57, Folder 4)
              (first published in "Moambe")
            - "Eshche spornye voprosy," 1908 (Box 57, Folder 5-6)
            - "Gazeta "Iveriia" i natsional'nost'," 1895 (Box 57, Folder 7)
            - "Gruzinskaia i russkaia sotsialdemokratiia" (Box 57, Folder 8)
              (abridged translation of the original article published in chveni Drosha". Translated by G. Eradze)
            - "Gruzinskii narod i natsionalizm," 1907 (Box 57, Folder 9)
            - "Malen'kii otvet na bol'shoi vopros," 1900 (Box 57, Folder 10)
            - "Nashi raznoglasiia," [1900 ?] (Box 57, Folder 11)
            - "Spornye voprosy," undated (Box 57, Folder 12)
            - "Zlobodnevnye voprosy," 1908 (Box 57, Folder 13)
          - Supplement: S. Khundadze about N. Zhordania (Box 57, Folder 14)
            (excerpt from his book Istoriia sotsializma v Gruzii. Holograph copy by V. Tsuladze)
        - Unidentified typescript (Box 57, Folder 15)
          (incomplete; enclosed holograph note by unidentified person leads probable attribution to G. Uratadze)
        - Notes (Box 57, Folder 16-17)
          (Haimson's research and scrap notes)
      - Bibliography: List of materials on history of Georgian Social-Democratic movement send to Leopold Haimson by V. Tsuladze (Box 57, Folder 18)
      - Biographical material for the Biographical Dictionary of Mensheviks
        - Biographical data on Georgian Mensheviks (Box 57, Folder 19)
          (written and corrected by M. Arsenidze, G. Eradze, and Tsintsadze)
        - Uratadze, Grigorii. Materials for his biography (Box 57, Folder 20)
          (by various sources)
      - Interviews with Georgian Mensheviks:
        - Typescripts:
          - Arsenidze, Razhden: see Sub-subseries III.3.2: Interviews (Box 27, Folders 14-17 and Box 28, Folders 1-8)
          - Eradze, Georgii: see Sub-subseries III.3.2: Interviews (Box 36, Folders 7-12)
          - Gegechkori, Evgenii: see Sub-subseries III.3.2: Interviews (Box 36, Folder 13)
        - Audio records: see Series XIV: Audio material--Subseries XIV: Interviews (Boxes 161-162)
          - Arsenidze, Razhden
          - Eradze, Georgii
          - Tsuladze, Vasilii
    - Sub-subseries III.3.8: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik Records, 1941-1964
      This sub-subseries comprises records of the major Menshevik publication Sotsialisticheskii vestnik, which include correspondence, publications, and extensive files of editorial materials that contain holograph manuscripts and typescripts for typesetting, drafts of articles, final revises with holograph notes, and galley proofs with holograph notes. Organized in three parts: correspondence, magazine issues, and editorial materials. Chronological order within each part.
      In the part of editorial materials, articles remain in original order, that is according to the issue's table of content, but for researchers' convenience, description provides their alphabetical list
      - Correspondence, 1942-1964
        - 1942 Schwarz, Solomon to Novoe russkoe slovo, January 29 (Box 58, Folder 1)
        - 1943 Schwarz, Solomon to "Neuen Volkszeitung", August 9 (In German) (Box 58, Folder 1)
        - 1957
          - Abramovich, Rafael to S. Schwarz (Box 58, Folder 2)
          - Ozol, Ivan to B. Nikolaevsky, November 27 (Box 58, Folder 2)
          - Sapir, Boris: correspondence with S. Schwarz, June-July (Box 58, Folder 2)
            (with Schwarz's replies and related materials, including letter of R. Abramovich)
          - Volkov, L. to Boris Nikolaevsky, December 28 (Box 58, Folder 3)
          - Unidentified to Editors, Vienna, December 10 (Box 58, Folder 3)
        - 1958 Lande, Lev. Letters to S. Schwarz, July 2 and 7 (Box 58, Folder 4)
        - 1964 Schwarz, Solomon. Letters to:
          - Iu.Denike, September 23 (Box 58, Folder 5)
          - Tat'iana Pavlovna, February 24 and March 4, (2 letters with related article) (Box 58, Folder 5)
      - Magazine issues, 1944-1964
        - 1944 #1-4; 19-20 (Box 58, Folder 6)
        - 1945 #17-18 (Box 58, Folder 7)
        - 1947 #9 (Box 58, Folder 8)
        - 1949 #8-9 (Box 58, Folder 8)
        - 1950 #1-4 (Box 58, Folder 9)
          (#4 has three copies)
        - 1951 #2-5; 8-12 (Box 58, Folder 10-12)
          (some issues - multiple copies)
        - 1952 #1-4; 9-12 (Box 58, Folder 13-14)
        - 1953 #1-4 (Box 58, Folder 15)
        - 1954 #2-4; 10-12 (Box 58, Folder 16-17)
        - 1955 #1; 4-8; index to issues of 1955 (Box 58, Folder 18-19)
          (index is an excerpt from#12)
        - 1956 #10-12 (Box 58, Folder 20)
        - 1957 #2-12 (Box 58, Folder 21-24)
        - 1958
          (two copies of each issue except #1)
          - #1-5 (Box 58, Folder 25-26)
          - #6-12 (Box 59, Folder 1-3)
        - 1959 #1-5; 7-12 (Box 59, Folder 4-7)
          (two copies of each issue)
        - 1960 #7; 10-12 (Box 59, Folder 8)
        - 1961 #1-9; 12 (Box 59, Folder 9-10)
        - 1962 #3, 4, 7-12 (Box 59, Folder 11)
        - 1963 #11-12 (Box 59, Folder 12)
        - 1964 Sbornik No.1 (Box 59, Folder 13)
        - Index to Sotsialisticheskii vestnik, 1940-1943, 1945-1952, 1954-1959, (photostat) (Box 59, Folder 14)
      - Editorial materials:
        - 1941 Articles, (typescripts with holograph notes)
          - Declaration of the Russian Social Democratic Party on the Soviet-German war, 1941 (Box 59, Folder 15)
            (carbon copy on The Socialist Courier letterhead)
          - Aleksandrova, Vera; Kefali, Mark; Khinoi, Mark. "Protest sotrudnikov 'Sotsialisticheskogo vestnika'" (Box 59, Folder 15)
          - Kefali, Mark; Nikolaevsky, Boris; Schwarz, Solomon. "V zashchitu partii" (Box 59, Folder 15)
          - Obozrevatel':
            - "Bel'giiskoe "soprotivlenie" (Box 59, Folder 16)
            - "Skandinavskie zarnitsy" (Box 59, Folder 16)
            - "Sotsialisticheskie otkliki na germano-sovetskuiu voinu" (Box 59, Folder 16)
          - Schwarz, Solomon:
            - "Derevnia pered voinoi" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Ekonomika v ogne voiny" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Krainie levye o germano-sovetskoi voine" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Manya Gordon, "Workrs Before and After Lenin" (Box 59, Folder 17)
              (book review)
            - "Na novom puti" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Nashe oboronchestvo i ego kritiki" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Neutralitaet der Sowjetunion" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "Novyi kurs" (Box 59, Folder 17)
            - "O edinom fronte" (Box 59, Folder 18)
            - "Opiat' voina s Finliandiei" (Box 59, Folder 18)
            - "Pered novymi zadachami" (Box 59, Folder 18)
            - "V finliandskoi s-d-ii" (Box 59, Folder 18)
            - "Voina i krestianstvo" (Box 59, Folder 18)
            - "Volna dorogovizny v SSSR" (Box 59, Folder 18)
          - Villar, Andre
            (column "Ot nashego korrespondenta")
            - "Frantsuzskoe profdvizhenie posle razgroma Frantsii" (Box 59, Folder 19)
            - "V chem oppozitsionnost' profsoiuzov?" (Box 59, Folder 19)
          - Unidentified. "Kiev pered sdachei" (Box 59, Folder 19)
        - 1942 Articles
          (typescripts with holograph notes)
          - Schwarz, Solomon:
            - "Amerikanskii posol v Moskve" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Byli gory Magnitnoi" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "K prodovol'stvennomu polozheniiu SSSR" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "K sudu nad finskimi sotsialistami" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Medvezh'ia zabota" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Na novom puti", (two articles) (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Ne o statistike, a o khlebe" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Novyi poriadok na vostoke Evropy" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Nuzhdaetsia li Sovetskii Soiuz v khlebe" (Box 60, Folder 1)
            - "Otgoloski Rimskogo protsessa" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Odna ili dve voiny?" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Pervaia ustupka" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - Pis'mo v redaktsiiu Novogo russkogo slova, January 29 1942 (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Problemy sovetskoi ekonomiki" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Russkie profsoiuzy" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Sel'skoe khoziaistvo v usloviiakh voiny", (two articles) (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Sovetskii Soiuz i Pol'sha" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Sotsial'noe litso VKP" (Box 60, Folder 2)
            - "Zernovoe khoziaistvo na pod'eme" (Box 60, Folder 2)
          - Various authors
            (mostly unsigned articles some of which may belong to Schwarz, and articles by various authors)
            - Ianushkis, I. "V okkupatsionnoi Litve" (Box 60, Folder 3)
            - Unidentified:
              - Iz partii: "V zagranichnoi delegatsii RSDRP" (Box 60, Folder 3)
              - "Kommunal'nye vybory v Shvetsii" (Box 60, Folder 3)
              - "Konferentsiia Mezhdunarodnoi Federatsii Profsoiuzov" (Box 60, Folder 3)
              - Po Rossii (Folder 3)
                - "Kak strana gotovilas' k voine" (Box 60, Folder 3)
                - "Pod natsistskoi piatoi" (Box 60, Folder 3)
                - "Tikhii geroizm" (Box 60, Folder 3)
              - "Po stranitsam sovetskoi pechati" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - "Poezdka Gamleta v Sovetskii Soiuz" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - "Programma bel'giiskoi sotsialisticheskoi partii" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - "V Pribaltike i na Ukraine" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - Zamechaniia k gl.2oi "Vliianie grazhdanskoi voiny na spros na zhenskii trud" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - Zamechaniia k stat'e "Upravlenie i organizatsiia truda v kolkhozakh" (Box 60, Folder 4)
              - Notes, (loose holograph notes) (Box 60, Folder 4)
        - 1943 Articles, (typescripts with holograph notes)
          - Schwarz, Solomon:
            - "Diktatura i industrializatsiia" (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - "Eshche o sotsial'nykh protsessakh v SSSR: Otvet strogomu kritiku" (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - "Inostrantsy v Sovetskom Soiuze" (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - "Mir s Finliandiei?" (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - "Narod i diktatura" (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - "O sotsial'nykh protsesakh v SSSR: Otvet t. Iugovu" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - Pis'ma v redaktsiiu Novogo russkogo slova, (two letters) (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "Putevaia" zametka" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "Rossiia i Pol'sha" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "Russische Gewerkschaften" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "SSSR segodnia" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "Svobodnaia Germaniia" (Box 60, Folder 6)
            - "V okkupirovannoi Rossii" (Box 60, Folder 7)
              (Russian and English)
            - "V osvobozhdennykh oblastiakh" (Box 60, Folder 7)
            - "Vo imia sotsial'nogo konservatizma?" (Box 60, Folder 7)
            - "Voina i sel'skoe khoziaistvo v SSSR" (Box 60, Folder 7)
            - "Vozvrashchenie k zhizni" (Box 60, Folder 7)
          - Various authors:
            (mostly includes unsigned articles some of which may belong to Schwarz, and articles by various authors)
            - "Avstriiskie rabochie na russkom fronte" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Edo Fimmen" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Po stranitsam sovetskoi pechati" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Pod znakom voiny" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Posle ubiistva tt. Erlikha i Al'tera" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Russkie rabochie v Germanii" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Voina i rabochii klass" (Box 60, Folder 8)
            - "Zagranichnaia Delegatsiia RSDRP" (Box 60, Folder 8)
              (article regarding the conflict)
          - Corrections, additions, notes (Box 60, Folder 9)
        - 1956
          - #4: Iasnyi, Naum. "Voprosy rabochei sily", (typescript of article with holograph notes) (Box 60, Folder 10)
          - #7-8: